Although living a virtuous, renunciate
and secluded life, when I reflect about
my day in the evenings, I feel like I
have still been pushed around all day
despite not having failed in any of the
aforementioned qualities. Why is that?
How do I stop being pushed around?
Yeah, assuming that the questioner here
is pushed around by his own mind, then
it's good of course to be established in
virtue. But that's not going to be
enough now. That is just the first step.
So keeping eight precepts is step one,
but there's a lot of room within those
eight precepts to still do all sorts of
things that come out of your mind
pressuring you. So to establish yourself
in the basic precepts right five plus
celibacy and the non-distraction that is
the starting point for any serious
mental development
um then yes you can adhere to those
precepts externally but the point is
then twofold one
understand well the the first point is
to that without establishing yourself in
the Bcept you're not even going to see
your own mind. So you need to set up
that boundary. Your mind will be running
into it. And that is why you can see aha
I've been going in the wrong direction
now. And because I'm keeping this
precepts, right? I I've put up that
fence and I'm determined to to not go
past it. That's where you see your mind
pushing you in that direction. So so you
can catch a glimpse that you have been
running with your mind. If you are at
the point of breaking a precept that
you're not breaking it but that so that
container of the precept is necessary to
even see what your mind is. That's their
aim. And then the second step is that
you just don't want to be uh keeping it
like that. But you now want to take that
principle of
understanding what it means to be
pressured by your own mind and you want
to make that the sole criteria for
whether something is wholesome or
unwome. So every time you give in to the
pressure of your mind that is out of
weakness on your part and you have to
then realize that the mind jitta cannot
actually force you to act. Might feel
like that but you are always there with
it giving in.
So out of carelessness you can forget
this right perspective and still go with
the mind. That's not good. Um but more
importantly you want to recognize yeah
the mind cannot actually
force me to to do things. I am there
with it. And that is why we often speak
about taking or discerning this attitude of
taking or discerning this attitude of
full complete responsibility like the
whole thing is up to you. M
>> and so if you then externally keep the
precepts and you live a fairly secluded
life but at the end of the day you look
back and you see yeah my mind was still
bossing me around all day long then that
means that within the context of those
precepts you need to refine it further.
You need to look at your sensory
strength for example like which things
am I attending through
uh during my during my day
and and just more generally
clarify what is mind what does it mean
to be pressured by my own mind and am I
still giving into that because I think
it's too painful if I don't or am I
recognizing no the training is to not
give into the pressure of the mind and
and to recognize when the mind is
pressuring you which could be about
something that is not at all covered by
the precepts. So that's the thing in the
beginning it it looks like it's a big
challenge to even keep those eight
precepts. Yes, that's that's a starting
point. At some point you'll recognize
okay I'm fairly solid now in keeping
those precepts that that fence is
getting more and more in the distance
now. You're not running into the fence
the whole time anymore. Um [snorts]
but uh so that's a good first step but
then you want to take it
more carefully and want to look more
closely because what do those precepts
cover? They cover your bodily behavior
and also your speech. You're not lying,
not any loot speech and and so on. Um
but uh the actual purification now needs
to happen on the mental level. what it
is that you are thinking about, what it
is that you accept and welcome and
delight in mentally or alternatively all
the things that you think shouldn't be
there mentally and you want to get rid
of um basically also hindrances that's
primarily on that level and that is
still the mind pressuring you there.
But you see, you're you're never going
to recognize any of that if the bodily
and the verbal behavior is not
restrained first. So that's the first
step. And yeah, if you if you purify
um the stream, let's say at the top of
the mountain, then it's impossible that
it becomes contaminated further
downstream. >> But um since we don't start in a neutral
>> But um since we don't start in a neutral
position, we first need to actually
discern the whole origin of the stream,
right? which is why yonikara is also a
necessary factor for the arising of the
right view. Yeah. All of that begins by
restraining bodily and verbal behavior
so that you even begin to see what is
chitta that which is pressuring you as
we talked about in the earlier
discussion. And then you want to
recognize that also on the mental level
on your on right the thoughts that you
welcome and delight in or want to get
rid of
there too jeta is pressuring you and so
there is also something as let's say
mental discipline keeping an eye on the
kinds of thoughts that you welcome and
delight and if they are essential you
shouldn't do that you should not delight
in those thoughts cut them off if you're
having entire conversations going on um
that are rooted in annoyance, ill will,
aversion, why is this happening to me,
self pity and all the rest of it that
can go on for a while and you cannot
notice it. All of that is there's still
pressure behind that be behind those
mental actions and so it can be somewhat
of a discovery to realize wait there is
such a thing as mental action.
I can actually also just stop certain
thoughts or at least not welcome and
enlighten them. And so I do have a
responsibility also for what is going on
mentally. >> And that is what you now want to start
>> And that is what you now want to start
looking into and developing. Because if
you do not welcome and delight anymore
in thoughts of sensuality, if you do not
welcome and delight ill will, annoyance,
thoughts of cruelty and so on, it's
going to be impossible that by body and
speech anything of that kind is going to
factory manifest. That's just
impossible. So if you tackle the problem
there right you're you're moving like that
right you're you're moving like that
that whole fence is like properly in the
distance now
>> so yeah somebody can be established in
virtue uh by which I take it to mean
he's just keeping the precepts
externally but to be accomplished in
virtue as the sudas often say
accomplished in virtue means that you
are not just conforming to a set of
rules externally but you understand that
what makes those rules by those rules
are there. But what makes breaking them
unh wholesome? Namely that breaking any
of those precepts means that you were
totally overpowered by the press of your
mind. >> It's impossible to break those rules
>> It's impossible to break those rules
otherwise. And so you want to understand
the principle and then you see what
makes something wholesome and unh
wholesome which has nothing to do with
what the world externally might think.
Has nothing to do with even specific
sets of rules that you adhere to.
Anything that comes out of you giving in
to the pressure of your own mind is unh
wholesome even if it's not covered by
the precepts.
That's the principle.
>> And so understanding this principle
means that whatever you do by body,
speech, and mind, you're going to ask
yourself, wait, why am I doing this now?
Why am I accepting, tolerating, going
with this? Or why am I resisting this?
Is it mind that I ask for it or is it
just there? And so you begin to question
your involvement with those phenomena
and see wait I'm also responsible for my
attitudes for what I welcome and delight
in and what I want to get rid of.
then you will um going to experience
more subtle manifestations of the same
pressure and the right the the mind
craving that's what pressure is
and yeah then mentally you shouldn't
give into that
and by not giving into those things
mentally if that becomes the level of your
if that becomes the level of your
practice now um then at the end of the
day you you will not feel that you have
been bossed around by your own mind
because you haven't left any corners for
your mind to be bossing you around
because you've now included that whole
mental domain
um in your responsibility.
Would you say it's useful trying to discern
you say it's useful trying to discern
first this principle of actually
referring your actions always to your
mind like throughout the day any
physical action any verbal action you
actually first and foremost obviously
it's within the precepts let's assume
>> you first and foremost always look at
your mind state if there's any potential
of agitating the mind if there's any
potential that the mind pressures you
towards it even if it's something
fairly wholesome you could say on the
physical and verbal level like studying
reading sutas making a project but you
see the mind wants to do it leaps
towards it
>> and to actually pay attention to that
tendency because that's where even
within precepts restraint and seclusion
the bossing around still happens
So basically with everything that you
are doing
>> you right you will have to ask yourself
wait why am I doing this and why am I
doing it specifically now
>> so then you can ask yourself okay what
would to happen if I'm not going to do
it now
>> and then not so much like what are going
to be the external consequences on the
world level no
>> um is your mind going to make a drama
about it if you don't do it now
>> if it does and you will be able to feel
that like oh yeah this is going to be a
bit annoying if I'm now not going to do
this that means that your mind is behind
there pressuring you to do it
>> and that's when you should not do it
>> and you see it doesn't then even matter
what it is that you're effectually going
to do
>> right not breaking any of the precepts
obviously but and in the beginning it might look
but and in the beginning it might look
like that everything that you do is
coming out of the craving like so
somebody here is okay mind is putting
pressure on me you take that message on
and then you realize well everything I
do is coming out pressure but that is
just because the craving the pressure
hasn't been discerned sufficiently
accurately. So that is the refinement that needs to
So that is the refinement that needs to
happen. So yeah the the mind will be
pushing you in some specific direction
and then the more you recognize that and
do not give in to that pressure the more
you will begin to realize that there's
actually a lot of space around it for
other things to do that do now not come
out of that pressure
>> and then you can do those things.
They're sort of parallel. Your mind
wants to pressure you this way and
you're just going to do something else
that doesn't come out of the pressure.
The pressure is still there. Pressure is
saying I want you to do this. You start
you start doing something else.
>> Meanwhile, keeping an eye on your mind
still wants you to do this.
>> So on the one hand, you resist the
direction in which your mind wants to
pressure you and then which other thing
you do doesn't even matter all that
much. >> So you also become less concerned with
>> So you also become less concerned with
what am I going to do? The emphasis
[clears throat] shifts to what am I not
going to do? But you see next day the
thing that the mind is pressuring you to
do now
can you could perhaps do it because now
the mind is not behind it pressuring
you. >> So whether something is right or wrong
>> So whether something is right or wrong
for you on a certain occasion is not
determined by any sort of external code
or conduct. It's fully determined
internally by whether your mind is
pushing you to do it or whether you are
in fact doing it. um not out of weakness
because the mind is behind you
pressuring you.
>> And that means but you see in order to
now find out is it is it okay to do this
or not you obviously need to see your
mind >> and um that you're only going to see
>> and um that you're only going to see
when you start with the virtue the
restraint and the seclusion
>> and the mind is not always putting
pressure when you did the same thing. So
this basically means that you have to be
on the ball the whole time.
>> And that's where the where the right
mindfulness comes in. The right
mindfulness is if I'm not going to do
what I want to do now, it's going to be
an issue. Issue in relation to will the
mind take it? Is it just going to be
sort of economous with it? It's okay, we
can do it some other time. No big deal.
Or is it going to be like, yeah, but I
really want to do this sort of now. Mhm.
>> And then and then you need to be in that
sense more rational and say well this is not
more rational and say well this is not
the right time to do it.
>> We might do it on some future occasion.
We don't know.
>> We will see.
And yeah uh that is all part of the
training. And then you also recognize
how futile it is to think that you can
just train for an hour in the morning
and an hour in the evening because this
just has to concern everything that you
do
>> 24/7 whether you're alone or with others
whether it's day or night
>> just as a parent is responsible for the
child and you cannot say I'm going to be
responsible for my child only for one
hour in the morning and an hour in the
evening [snorts] right either you say
I'm bound up with this child I need to
look after it or else you're not the
responsible parent.
And sometimes when one isn't sure about
or one has the feeling okay this is
probably not coming out of a pressure
the Buddha usually recommend as well
before while and after an action by body
speech or mind to actually keep that
context of okay you might have started
off well
>> but actually while doing it you realize
the mind takes over pressures you and
then you actually need to have the
capacity to stop yourself in in the
middle of yeah maybe a project that you
really want to finish but you say hold
on I'm not going to do this now
>> yeah that was his advice to his own son
>> for body speech and minds before you
going to do something question
>> while you are engaged in those action
because you see while being engaged in
an action you can still stop and start
doing something else
>> because you're the one who is acting
>> right
>> and then afterwards you can say wait did
I lose perspective
>> or not or maybe it started out right but
somewhere it that took a bit of a funny
turn >> and yeah that's useful to have some time
>> and yeah that's useful to have some time
uh at the end of the day to look back
and then in particular like you know did
I give in to pressure of the own mind or
not and then to determine well I I I
need to pay more attention next time
because you don't gain anything from
living with a mind that is wild and not
trained and tainted because [snorts]
at any moment anything can happen and
you will have to meet that situation
with your mind.
>> So the more uh the mind is opposed to
you the more difficult it will be for
you to deal with the situation
accurately. >> So you benefit from living with a mind
>> So you benefit from living with a mind
that is tainted trained composed
listening to you so so that you can live
your life together harmoniously rather
than always needing to fight your own
mind. and then deal with all sorts of
external stuff. That's a very poor
situation to be in. So even if things
are relatively okay now, you still want
to recognize there's no guarantee it's
going to stay like that. All sorts of
unfortunate situations can happen. And
then I need to deal with it.
>> And it's going to be much better if I
can deal with it with a mind that is
there next to me than having a mind over
against me.